{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This battle featured fierce fighting over the village of Ponyri, which gave one side the opportunity to launch Operation Kutuzov. Walther Model and Erich von Manstein aimed to pincer the namesake salient during this battle. Codenamed Citadel, this battle was delayed so that one side could wait for more Panthers. Tigers and T-34s clashed at Prokhorovka in, for ten points, what 1943 battle on the Eastern Front, the largest tank battle in history?",
      "answer": "Battle of Kursk"
    },
    {
      "question": "Note: two answers required. At an embassy owned by one of these countries in the other country, an indoor soccer game was interrupted by commandos setting off a bomb under the floor, beginning Operation Chavin de Huantar. That raid ended a hostage crisis that began on the 63rd birthday of the emperor of one of these two countries; the hostages were taken by members of the Tupac Amaru terrorist group, which was based in the other country. A corrupt politician who was the first man of Asian descent to become President of a non-Asian country is a citizen of these two countries. For ten points, name this pair of countries that fought an extradition battle over Alberto Fujimori.",
      "answer": [
        "Japan and Peru",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Merton wrote “The Seven-Story Mountain” about his life in one of these places. The site of the burning bush is supposedly located at one of these places on the Sinai Peninsula in Egypt. The most important Orthodox examples of these places are located on Mt. Athos in Greece. In the 1530s, Henry VIII closed many of these places down in the “Dissolution” of them. For ten points, name these institutions where religious devotees live in a community, including monks and nuns.",
      "answer": "monastery"
    },
    {
      "question": "While surveying the grounds for this project, its architect crushed his foot when it was trapped by a passing ferry, resulting in a tetanus infection that killed him. A physician involved in the creation of this project named Andrew Smith coined the name of a sickness that afflicted many of the workers along it, “caisson disease.” This project began in 1869 and was opened in 1883 as Chester Arthur walked along it. Washington Roebling oversaw the creation of, for ten points, what bridge connecting Manhattan to a namesake New York borough?",
      "answer": "Brooklyn Bridge"
    },
    {
      "question": "The majority opinion in this case cites Pugsley v. Sellmeyer when noting that it “does not relate to regulation of the length of skirts or the type of clothing.” Abe Fortas delivered the majority opinion in this case, which argued that “the petitioners were quiet and passive.” This case arose out of demonstrations in support of the Christmas Truce. This case’s namesake test has been used to see if school policies violate constitutional rights. For ten points, name this 1969 case about a ban on the wearing of black armbands to protest the Vietnam War.",
      "answer": "Tinker v. Des Moines"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was accused of having “undertaken to be the hero of the night” among a group described as a “motley rabble of saucy boys.” This man, who is buried in the Old Granary Burying Ground, was once thought to have been a slave of William Brown. A protest against the Townshend Acts ended with the death of this man, followed by four other deaths; their killers were defended by John Adams. For ten points, name this black man who was the first to die in the Boston Massacre.",
      "answer": "Crispus Attucks"
    },
    {
      "question": "Following a 2006 war, “The Right of Peace” advocated for residents of this territory to live in one neighboring country while holding citizenship in another. The Mukataa of a political leader of this territory was once found in its capital city of Ramallah until it was raided by the IDF in 2002. The founder of Fatah, Yasser Arafat, administered his main organization from this territory, which is named for its position relative to the Jordan River. For ten points, name this territory that makes up the State of Palestine along with the Gaza Strip.",
      "answer": "West Bank"
    },
    {
      "question": "After serving as a Confederate soldier at the Battle of Shiloh, this man joined the Union Army at the behest of James Mulligan. When this man heard that an officer in his “Rear Guard” handed over a girl to be eaten by cannibals, he attempted to place the blame on trader Tippu Tip; that incident occurred while he led an expedition to relieve Emin Pasha. In 1869, this man was sent to relieve a Scottish missionary who was searching for the source of the Nile. For ten points, name this explorer who legendarily asked “Dr. Livingstone, I presume?”",
      "answer": "Henry Morton Stanley"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1998, the National Film Registry preserved a film of this event created by camera shop owner Barley Elliot. Gig Harbor was one of the endpoints of the central structure involved in this event, which wasdesignedbyLeonMoisseiff.AdognamedTubbyperishedinthisevent,inwhich40mileanhourwinds caused an irregular torsional vibrational mode that led the central structure to flap. For ten points, name this disaster along a structure nicknamed “Galloping Gertie” crossing the Puget Sound in Washington.",
      "answer": [
        "collapse or failure, etc. of the Tacoma Narrows Bridge",
        "Galloping Gertie in place of Tacoma Narrows Bridge before “Galloping” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In one of this author’s novels, Urania Cabral lives under the Trujillo dictatorship in the Dominican Republic. This author, who fictionalized his time at a military academy in The Time of The Hero, created the character of Pedro Camacho, who works for Radio Panamericano during the 1950s. For ten points, name this winner of the 2010 Nobel Prize in Literature, a Peruvian author who wrote Aunt Julia and the Scriptwriter.",
      "answer": "Mario Vargas Llosa"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The art of these people prominently features falcon warriors in a non-Chilean Birdman cult that formed part of a “Ceremonial Complex.” These people were succeeded by the Woodland culture, and they succeeded the Hopewell people. These people erected a series of cedar posts dubbed Woodhenge and constructed an earthen pyramid at Cahokia. For ten points, name this pre-Columbian Native American culture that inhabited land around a namesake river.",
        "answer": "Mississippian culture"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This mound at Cahokia is the largest Mississippian-era pyramid, of comparable area to the Great Pyramid of Giza.",
        "answer": "Monks Mound"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 1500s, this city’s House of Trade handled a 20 percent tax on all precious metals passing into its country. Christopher Columbus is buried underneath a cathedral in this city, which is located on the Guadalquivir River. Legends claim that Heracles founded this inland city and a nearby port city as he passed through the Strait of Gibraltar. Twelve years after the fall of Cordoba, this city was captured by Ferdinand III of Castile in 1248. For ten points, name this largest city in Andalusia.",
        "answer": [
          "Seville",
          "Sevilla"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Seville lost its economic importance in the late 16th century to this port city on the mouth of the Guadalquivir River, which empties into a gulf named for this city.",
        "answer": "Gulf of Cadiz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the adopted home of Hugh Cholmondeley [chum-lee], the man who first coined the term “white hunter” for safari hunting westerners; he belonged to this country’s scandalous white Happy Valley Set. A dispute over this country’s north caused the Shifta War. Dedan Kimathi was killed in this country while leading a rebellion that led to the jailing of the Kapenguria Six. The Mau Mau Rebellion occurred in, for ten points, what country first led by Jomo Kenyatta?",
        "answer": "Kenya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dedan Kimathi was a member of this ethnic group, the largest in Kenya. Members of this group, as well as the Meru, Maasai, and Embu peoples, joined together in the Mau Mau Rebellion.",
        "answer": "Kikuyu people or Gikuyu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A cartoon satirizing this program shows a group of leaders dressed as Boy Scouts marching in front of a bus with the word “Ruin” printed on it. Hjalmar Schacht was the president of an institution reorganized by this program. A $200 million loan was provided as part of this plan, which created the Reichsmark. Owen Young named a successor to this program that included a twenty percent reduction in certain debts. For ten points, name this 1924 plan intended to help Germany pay its World War I reparations.",
        "answer": "Dawes Plan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The reparations owed by Germany were legally laid out in part 8 of the Treaty of Versailles, which opens with this highly controversial statement assigning all loss to German causes. This article is often cited as a precursor to the rise of Nazi aggression.",
        "answer": "Article 231 or the War Guilt Clause"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A school of composers named for this city was led by Palestrina. When a 14-year-old Mozart visited this city, he listened to two performances of Gregorio Allegri’s Miserere [miz-eh-rare-ee] and transcribed the piece from memory. Ottorino Respighi’s trilogy of tone poems about this city include depictions of its Fountains, including the Triton Fountain and the Trevi Fountain, and its Pines, such as the “Pines of the Appian Way.” For ten points, name this Italian city.",
        "answer": "Rome"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Louis XIV [14] established the Prix [pree] de Rome, which grants French painters and composers a scholarship to study in Rome. This composer of The Pearl Fishers and an opera about Ivan the Terrible won the prize in 1857.",
        "answer": "Georges Bizet"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Amerigo Vespucci may have been named after a son of this man who had died in a boar hunting accident in present day Romania. That son, Emeric, was born to this man by a Bavarian princess named Gisela. The doctrine of primogeniture was used to justify this man’s succession following the death of Geza rather than that of this man’s uncle, who ruled portions of Transdanubia. This man was baptized at Esztergom [ess-ter-gohm], where he now serves as the patron saint. For ten points, name this first King of Hungary.",
        "answer": "Stephen I of Hungary or Saint Stephen"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Saint Stephen was a member of this ruling dynasty of Hungary, which died out in the early 14th century.",
        "answer": "Arpad Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this film, a bag of diamonds is given as a bribe to convince a man to redirect a train. Near the end of this film, a ring inscribed “Whoever saves one life, saves the world” is given to the title character. At age 3, Oliwia Dabrowska played a girl in a red coat in this film, whose director refused to take a salary for it. Itzhak Stern assists the protagonist of this film, in which Amon Goth oversees a concentration camp. For ten points, name this Steven Spielberg film about a factory owner who saves over 1,000 Jews during the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "Schindler’s List"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The film Schindler’s List was based on a novel by this Australian author, whose 1972 novel The Chant of Jimmie Blacksmith is a fictionalized story of the 19th century bushranger Jimmy Governor.",
        "answer": "Thomas Keneally"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man led a group of Austrasians against Chilperic and Ragenfrid at the Battle of Vincy. This man was imprisoned by his rival Plectrude and fought with her for Austrasia. He came to the aid of Odo of Aquitaine in a battle where he arranged his army, entirely made up of infantry, into a square to defeat the Umayyad cavalry. For ten points, name this Frankish “Mayor of the Palace” who won the Battle of Tours, preventing an Islamic advance into Gaul, and who was the grandfather of Charlemagne.",
        "answer": "Charles Martel or Charles the Hammer"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Umayyad general and governor of Cordoba was defeated and killed at the Battle of Tours.",
        "answer": "Abd al-Rahman or Abdul Rahman"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Watergate",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who resigned after the scandal.",
          "answer": "Richard M. Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political group whose headquarters at the Watergate hotel was burgled.",
          "answer": "Democratic National Committee or DNC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position held by Elliot Richardson until the Saturday Night Massacre, when he resigned rather than fire the special prosecutor.",
          "answer": "Attorney General"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fundraising group that paid legal expenses for the Watergate burglars, in addition to its stated purpose.",
          "answer": "CREEP"
        },
        {
          "question": "FBI agent who was the anonymous source “Deep Throat.”",
          "answer": "W. Mark Felt, Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Head of “the Plumbers” and organizer of the burglary, supervising it with E. Howard Hunt.",
          "answer": "G. Gordon Liddy"
        },
        {
          "question": "White House Chief of Staff who was convicted of obstruction of justice for his role in the scandal.",
          "answer": "H.R. Haldeman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deputy who was the second to resign, after Richardson, in the Saturday Night Massacre.",
          "answer": "William Ruckelshaus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Joan of Arc",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Home country of Joan, for whom she opposed England in the Hundred Years’ War.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose siege she helped lift, earning her the nickname “Maid of” this place.",
          "answer": "Orleans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Method by which she was executed for heresy.",
          "answer": "burning at the stake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Additional charge added to Joan’s crimes, as heresy alone was not punishable by death.",
          "answer": [
            "cross-dressing",
            "equivalents, such as wearing male clothing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City to which she brought the Dauphin Charles to be crowned King in 1429.",
          "answer": "Reims , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either the pope who cleared Joan’s name in 1455 or the pope who named her a saint in 1920.",
          "answer": [
            "Callixtus III",
            "Benedict XV"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Any one of the three saints who appeared to Joan in her vision; one was a 4th century AD martyr from Alexandria.",
          "answer": "Saints Catherine of Alexandria, Michael, and/or Margaret of Antioch"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Joan was captured in 1430 by the English.",
          "answer": "Compiegne"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Revolutionaries",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where Yukio Mishima committed seppuku in 1970 after a failed coup d’etat.",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose National Army was joined by Lakshmi Sahgal, who fought for independence from Britain.",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Metis leader and revolutionary Louis Riel fought in the Red River Rebellion.",
          "answer": "Canada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose 1791-1804 revolution was led by ex-slave Toussaint L’Ouverture.",
          "answer": "Haiti"
        },
        {
          "question": "African country where Ahmed Ben Bella fought for independence from the French.",
          "answer": "Algeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who led Philippine forces against Spain and the US; in 1899, he became the first President of the Philippines.",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-violent group in Nazi Germany that included the executed student Sophie Scholl.",
          "answer": "White Rose or Die Weisse Rose"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rvolutionary who called for land reforms in Mexico under the Plan de Ayala.",
          "answer": "Emiliano Zapata"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Religious practices in this modern-day country include the Shaking Tent ritual and a regular re-burial of the corpses of those who had died peacefully, the Feast of the Dead. The Montagnais lived in this nation, where the (20 pts)",
        "Northwest Company operated. The city of (10 pts)",
        "Stadacona was visited by the explorer Jacques Cartier in what is now, for ten points, what country where Samuel de Champlain founded Quebec City?"
      ],
      "answer": "Canada"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man signed a treaty with Chief Bowl to guarantee Cherokee land rights, though his friendship with the natives led to a feud with senator William Stanberry, who this man attacked with a (20 pts)",
        "cane. This man was replaced from his highest post by Mirabeau Lamar after refusing to join the Confederacy. As a general, this man took only (10 pts)",
        "18 minutes to win the Battle of San Jacinto against Santa Anna. For ten points, name this fighter for Texan independence and namesake of the most populous city in Texas."
      ],
      "answer": "Sam Houston"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This thinker thought that the “sublime” was the feeling of experiencing something that feels infinite when one rationally knows that it is not. This philosopher defined the title concept as “man’s (20 pts)",
        "emergence from his self-imposed immaturity” in an essay asking “What Is Enlightenment?” This thinker explored the moral law in his (10 pts)",
        "Metaphysics of Morals and the earlier Groundwork. For ten points, name this German philosopher who formulated the categorical imperative and wrote the Critique of Pure Reason."
      ],
      "answer": "Immanuel Kant"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Xanthippus, the father of Pericles, rivaled this man and was ostracized, but was later allowed to return and replaced this man as commander at the Battle of Mycale. This man used the silver from the (20 pts)",
        "Laurium mines to build 100 triremes, over the objections of his rival, Aristides. This (10 pts)",
        "naval commander was exiled to Argos, and earlier won the Battle of Artemisium. For ten points, name this Athenian who led Greek forces to victory at Salamis."
      ],
      "answer": "Themistocles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A Czech artist from this movement created paintings like The Bulgarian Tsar Simeon and The Battle of Grunwald as part of his Slav Epic. Alphonse Mucha was an artist in this movement, in which an architect developed the “biomorphic whiplash” (20 pts)",
        "curvilinear style in his Hotel Tassel. Hector Guimard created the Abbesses Station in this style as part of his design of the Paris Metro. The Chicago (10 pts)",
        "World’s Fair showcased lamps created in this style by Louis Comfort Tiffany. Art Deco essentially replaced, for ten points, what 19th century art style with a name meaning “new art?”"
      ],
      "answer": "Art Nouveau"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader attempted to conquer Viborg from Sweden, but was stopped by the forces of Knut Posse. After the death of his first wife Maria of Tver, this man was encouraged by the Pope to marry the ex-Byzantine princess (20 pts)",
        "Zoe Palaiologos. This man famously forced Akhmat to retreat during the Great Stand on the Ugra River, which ended Tatar rule in his lands. Later in his rule, he carried out a mass (10 pts)",
        "renovation of the walls of the Kremlin. For ten points, name this grand prince of Moscow, the first to gather the lands of Rus under one crown."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ivan III Vasilyevich",
        "Ivan the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A million-acre grant owned by this man was sold in the Bingham Purchase. This man, who died in 1806 after swallowing a chicken bone, was sent with Gouvernor Morris on a mission to Elizabethtown to negotiate prisoner exchanges. This man became the (20 pts)",
        "youngest major general in the Continental Army after his service at Yorktown. This man, who was succeeded in his highest post by Timothy Pickering, had earlier employed eighty yoke of (10 pts)",
        "oxen to transport artillery to Boston during a namesake expedition. For ten points, name this American general who later served as the first Secretary of War."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry Knox"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Until 1924 in Japan, geishas used a variety of this object known as a senko-dokei. In the 1200s, al-Jazari developed one of these devices that relies on a candle. Lewis Mumford traced the medieval development of these objects in a work that argued that these, not (20 pts)",
        "steam engines, were central to the Industrial Revolution. The clepsydra was a type of these devices that relied on the pouring of (10 pts)",
        "water. An 1876 song gave the name “grandfather” to tall standing types of, for ten points, what timekeeping devices?"
      ],
      "answer": "clocks"
    }
  ]
}